Norman Corwin Papers
Norman Corwin Papers
- Productions of Corwin
  - Radio programs, individual
    - An American in England, radio series transmitted live from England via shortwave, based on Corwin’s trip to England for CBS in 1942
      - Recording, Episode 10: Clipper Home
        Last of the AMERICAN IN ENGLAND series, written and directed by Corwin and broadcast from new York on December 22, 1942. The program is based on the author's trip home from England via West Africa and Brazil. Score composed and conducted by Lyn Murray. The script is published in UNTITLED AND OTHER RADIO DRAMAS.
        - Clipper Home [disc 1 of 2], Dec 22, 1942; corwin_0144; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 4)
        - Clipper Home [disc 2 of 2], Dec 22, 1942; corwin_0145; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 4)
    - The Anatomy of Sound, 26 by Corwin #18
      - Correspondence, notes, photographs (284), 1941; 1955,; 1965-1966,; undated (Box 17)
      - Recording
        Written, directed and produced by Corwin as the 18th of the series 26 BY CORWIN, and broadcast from KNX, Hollywood, over CBS, on September 7, 1941. The narrator was Gale Sondergaard, who had won an Academy award for her portrayal of Mrs. Dreyfus in the film ZOLA. The script was published in the volume MORE BY CORWIN.
        - The Anatomy of Sound, 09/07/1942; corwin_0206; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Anne Rutledge
      See also Productions by others: O'Brien, Joel for recorded version.
      - Correspondence (133, 283), 1942-1946; 1951,; 1957,; 1961,; 1964-1968 (Box 17)
      - Manuscript fragment (283) (Box 17)
      - Publicity (283), 1950 (Box 17)
      - Typescript (56) (Box 17)
    - Appointment, 26 by Corwin #5
      - Correspondence (285), 1941 (Box 17)
      - Manuscript (285), original typescript (Box 17)
      - Recording
        Broadcast over CBS on June 1, 1941, as the fifth program of the 26 BY CORWIN series. It was Corwin's own least favorite of the 26, although a later production,in England, starring Leslie Banks, was given high praise by the Manchester Guardian. On the disc's label is printed that the disc is CBS Repeat. Also there is a hand written note indicating that the record is personal property of Norman Corwin.
        See also Productions by others: O'Brien, Joel for alternate recorded version.
        - Appointment [disc 1 of 2], 06/01/1941; corwin_0112; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Appointment [disc 2 of 2], 06/01/1941; corwin_0113; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Ballad for Americans, See Pursuit of Happiness below.
    - Between Americans
      - Correspondence (286), 1941-1967 (gaps) (Box 17)
      - Manuscripts, incomplete (56, 286), undated (Box 17)
      - Publicity (286), 1941; 1951 (Box 17)
    - The Charter in the Saucer
      - Recording (203)
        Written by Corwin for United nations Radio and first broadcast by the BBC on Oct. 4, 1955, with Sir Laurence Olivier playing the role of Frabjoy. This was one of few Corwin shows that he did not direct, and he was very unhappy with the casting of Vuz. The program was heard throughout the English-speaking world, but not in the United States. By 1955 the American networks were no longer giving "free" time to UN shows. Unpublished. See item #59 - script.
        - The Charter in the Saucer, part 1 of 2, 10/04/1955; corwin_0365; 1/2 inch audio tape (Box 31)
        - The Charter in the Saucer, part 2 of 2, 10/04/1955; corwin_0366; 1/2 inch audio tape (Box 31)
      - Script (59), 1955 (Box 17)
    - Citizen of the World
      - Promotional packet (70), 1949; printed material; photographs (Box 17)
    - The Cliché Expert, Columbia Presents Corwin, Season 1 #9
      - Recording
        Ninth in the first COLUMBIA PRESENTS CORWIN series, this was broadcast over CBS on May 2, 1944, under the direction of the author. Roland Young starred as the cliche [sic] expert. Betty Comdel and Adolph Green, in one of their first radio appearances, "testified" on the music cliche [sic]. The script was based on the series of "Cliche Expert" magazine piece by the humorist Frank Sullivan. Others in the cast included John McGovern, the newscaster Robert Trout, Jackson Beck, Ralph Bell, Kermit Murdock, Paul Mann, Robert dryden, Allen Drake, Gene Leonard. A handwritten note on the disc's label indicates that this is Corwn's copy.
        - The Cliche Expert [disc 1 of 2], 05/02/1944; corwin_0165; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - The Cliche Expert [disc 2 of 2], 05/02/1944; corwin_0166; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 5)
    - "Corwin Show For AVO"
      - Recording
        - Corwin Show For AVO [disc 1 of 2], 06/24/1946; corwin_0102; Lacquer discs/acetates
          On the sleeve's label is written: "Note to Martin Bush: I cannot identify this record until a tape is made of it. When this is done, I will furnish descriptive data to attach." Disc label reads: Office of International Information and Cultural Affairs. The show is in French. In pencil is written: "Probably On a Note of Triumph."
        - Corwin Show For AVO [disc 2 of 2], 06/24/1946; corwin_0103; Lacquer discs/acetates
          On the sleeve's label is written: "Note to Martin Bush: I cannot identify this record until a tape is made of it. When this is done, I will furnish descriptive data to attach." Disc label reads: Office of International Information and Cultural Affairs. The show is in French. In pencil is written: "Probably On a Note of Triumph." Also there is a handwritten note in French, for a reference check the record's image files.
    - Could Be
      - Recording, on disc
        Presented over NBC on OCtober 19, 1949; written, directed and produced by Corwin during the period he served as Chief of Special projects for United Nations Radio. Martin Gabel narrated; Ben Grauer, Gerald Kean, Gibson Parker and Paul Mann were among those in the cast. Alexander Semmler composed and conducted an original score. The broadcast was repeated over NBC shortly afterward. COULD BE is published as the end-piece in the book OVERKILL AND MEGALOVE, World Publishing, 1962. Additional data in Envelope 61.
        - Could Be [disc 1 of 3], 10/19/1949; corwin_0249; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Could Be [disc 2 of 3], 10/19/1949; corwin_0250; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Could Be [disc 3 of 3], 10/19/1949; corwin_0251; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Recording, on tape (200)
        Tape of radio production of COULD BE. Broadcast over NBC on Sept. 11, 1949, and repeated on the same network two weeks later. The text was published in the volume OVERKILL AND MEGALOVE, together with a foreword by the author, and appears on pp 83-114. The broadcast was later carried by radio systems throughout most of the English-speaking world, and translated into many languages for dissemination among other member nations of the UN. A complete record of these subsequent broadcasts is available at United Nations Radio, for which Corwin wrote, directed and produced the program.
        - COULD BE, part 1 of 3, 09/11/1949; corwin_0367; 1/2 inch audio tape (Box 31)
        - COULD BE, part 2 of 3, 09/11/1949; corwin_0368; 1/2 inch audio tape (Box 31)
        - COULD BE, part 3 of 3, 09/11/1949; corwin_0359; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 31)
      - Script (61), 1949-1951; typescript original; carbon of German translation; galley proofs; one published article not by Corwin (Box 17)
      - Translation, German ("Es koennte sein"), 1950 (Box 17)
      - Translation, Norwegian ("Kan Hende--?"), 1951 (Box 17)
      - Miscellaneous, correspondence, clippings, galleys for printed version (Box 17)
    - Daybreak, 26 by Corwin #8
      - Correspondence (62, 289), 1941; 1945; 1955 (Box 18)
      - Manuscript and notes (289) (Box 18)
      - Recording
        Produced as the eighth program of 26 BY CORWIN over CBS on June 22, 1941. Frank Gallup was the Pilot, and La Coehlo, the Brazilian contralto, sang the "Xango". Lyn Murray composed and conducted the score. This script was a favorite of Carl Van Doren who included it in his collaborative anthology THREE READERS. It is published among the playas in THIRTEEN BY CORWIN. A note on the sleeve's label indicates that other data is in Envelope 62.
        - Daybreak [disc 1 of 2], 06/22/1941; corwin_0179; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 6)
        - Daybreak [disc 2 of 2], 06/22/1941; corwin_0180; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Script (62), mimeo; correspondence (Box 18)
    - Descent of the Gods
      - Correspondence (288), 1941; 1946-1648,; 1956,; 1958,; 1963,; 1966,; undated; also includes a few clippings (Box 18)
      - Manuscript and notes (287) (Box 18)
    - Document A/777, alternate title: Universal Declaration of Human Rights
      See also Concerts: Celebration of First Anniversary of Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
      - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 18)
      - Recording, on disc
        First broadcast on March 26, 1950, over the Mutual Broadcasting System. Written, directed and produced by Corwin during his service as Chief of Special Projects for United Nations Radio. Participating in the program were Van Heflin as narrator, Maurice Evans, Lee Cobb, Charles Boyer, Reginald Gardiner, Jose Ferrer, Jean Hersholt, Lena Horne, Laurence Olivier, Vincent Price, Robert Ryan, Edward G. Robinson, Richard Baseheart, Charles Laughton, Marsha Hunt, Alexander Knox, Emlyn Williams, Joan Crawford. Lyn Murray composed and conducted. A tape of this production is also part of the Syracuse Collection. the broadcast was widely heard throughout the world, through the UN foreign offices. Script unpublished; additional data in Envelope.
        - Document A/777 [disc 1 of 2], 03/26/1950; corwin_0273; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Document A/777 [disc 2 of 2], 03/26/1950; corwin_0274; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Recording, on tape (201)
        First broadcast on March 26, 1950, over the Mutual Broadcasting System, and later carried over the national radio systems of most of the member states of the UN. It attracted particular attention in the U.S. and Great Britain, and was widely reviewed. The script was not published in the U.S., but was produced as a book in Japan, translated by Jiro Nanye. Corwin wrote, directed and produced the program at the instance of United Nations Radio, for which he was then Chief of Special Projects, to commemorate the anniversary of the signing of the UN's Universal Declaration of Human Rights by the General Assembly meeting in Paris. Most of the production was done in Hollywood; some sections came from New York.
        - DOCUMENT A/777, part 1 of 2, 03/26/1950; corwin_0361; 1/2 inch audio tape (Box 31)
        - DOCUMENT A/777, part 1 of 2, 03/26/1950; corwin_0362; 1/2 inch audio tape (Box 31)
      - Translation, Dutch, 1951; mimeo; letter (Box 18)
      - Translation, Spanish, mimeo (Box 18)
      - Typescript (64), 1951; includes marked-up copy of United Nations published text (Box 18)
      - Work cuts
        This broadcast was assembled from scenes and sound track recorded separately, over a period of two weeks, and in far-flung places. These discs consist of three such work cuts: [unreadable] then Prime Minister of New Zealand, Sidney Z. Holland, speaking of the social accomplishments of his country, in his office in Wellington, N.Z. [On the disc's label is written: "Contribution from the Hon. Sidney G. Holland, Prime Minister of New Zealand, for Norman Corwin's U.N. Programme [sic] on Human Rights. Sixty words. (Copy for Los Angeles). A note on the sleeve's label refers to Tape No. 24 in this collection. Information about the date is not presented on the disc. The date was found on the RadioGOLDINdex, Copyright 2012, David Goldin. The United Nations Audio Library/ UN Radio Classics has audio file of the entire program.
        - Document A/777 - Work cuts [disc 1], 04/17/1950; corwin_0136; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Document A/777 - Work cuts [disc 2], 04/17/1950; corwin_0137; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Document A/777 - Work cuts [disc 3], 04/17/1950; corwin_0138; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Document A/777 - Work cuts [disc 4], 04/17/1950; corwin_0139; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Dorie Got A Medal, Columbia Presents Corwin, Season 1 #8
      - Recording
        Broadcast on April 25, 1944 as the 8th in the first COLUMBIA PRESENTS CORWIN series. Josh White was the singing narrator, Canada Lee the speaking narrator. Music was by Mary Lou Williams and Jeff Alexander. Others in the cast were Early Hyman, Jim Backus and Laura Duncan. On the sleeve's label is written that additional data is in Envelope 174. There is a hand written note on the disc's label indicating that this is Corwin's copy.
        - Dorie Got A Medal [disc 1 of 2], 04/25/1944; corwin_0126; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Dorie Got A Medal [disc 2 of 2], 04/25/1944; corwin_0127; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Double Concerto, 26 by Corwin #12
      - Correspondence (290), 1941-1965 (gaps) (Box 18)
      - Manuscript (290) (Box 18)
      - Recording
        Produced and directed by the author over CBS on July 20, 1941, as the 12th of 26 By Corwin. Stars Peter Donald, Paul Stewart, Morgan Farley and Rosaline Greene. The script was published in MORE BY CORWIN, with notes on the production attached. A note on the sleeve's label indicates that material in the program contained in Envelope no. 173. On the disc's label is printed: "Number Eleven "Double Concerto"
        - Double Concerto Part One [disc 1 of 2], 07/20/1941; corwin_0163; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Double Concerto Part Two [disc 2 of 2], 07/20/1941; corwin_0164; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - El Capitan and the Corporal, Columbia Presents Corwin, Season 1 #19
      - Correspondence (65), 1944; 1946,; undated (Box 18)
      - Recording
        Presented over CBS on July 25, 1944, as the 19th of the first COLUMBIA PRESENTS CORWIN series. Katherine Locke (later to become Mrs. Corwin) was co-starred with Joseph Julian. Kermit Murdock appeared as the Fat Man. Burl Ives was the travelling minnesinger. The musical score was composed by Alexander Semmler. Published in UNTITLED AND OTHER RADIO DRAMAS. On the sleeve's label is written that additional data is in Envelope 65.
        - El Capitan and The Corporal [disc 1 of 2], 07/25/1944; corwin_0120; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - El Capitan and The Corporal [disc 2 of 2], 07/25/1944; corwin_0121; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Script (65), 1944 (Box 18)
    - Esther, 26 by Corwin #15
      See also Operas: Esther.
      - Recording
        Presented over CBS on August 17, 1941, as the 15th program of the 26 By Corwin series, and the second of three programs on Biblical themes. Lyn Murray wrote an original score to a libretto by Corwin, based on the Biblical Book of Esther. Corwin regarded his contribution to it as the poorest to any musical production in his output. Martin Gable appeared in the role of Haman. Other credits, unavailable at this writing, are indicated on the disc itself. The opera enjoyed some popularity, and was done by groups theatrically around the country. The libretto is unpublished, but the lyric of the Queen and Murray's music to it were independently published as a song entitled LOVE. There is a note on the sleeve's label that additional data is in Envelope 165. On the disc's labels is printed: "For reference recording only"
        - Esther, Parts 1 and 2, 08/17/1941; corwin_0154; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Fear Itself
      - Recording
        A program written to mark the fifth anniversary of the end of the European phase of World War II. Presented over the Mutual Broadcasting System on May 7, 1950. Martin Gabel narrated. The author produced and directed, for United Nations Radio.
        - Fear Itself [disc 1 of 6], 05/07/1950; corwin_0255; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Fear Itself [disc 2 of 6], 05/07/1950; corwin_0256; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Fear Itself [disc 3 of 6], 05/07/1950; corwin_0257; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Fear Itself [disc 4 of 6], 05/07/1950; corwin_0258; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Fear Itself [disc 5 of 6], 05/07/1950; corwin_0259; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Fear Itself [disc 6 of 6], 05/07/1950; corwin_0260; Lacquer discs/acetates
      - Translation, Spanish, undated; manuscript; mimeo (Box 18)
    - For the Planting of Trees at Brandeis
      - Manuscript, "This Ground Shall Remember" (99), 1954-1956; typescript wth annotations; printed broadside (Box 18)
        See also Correspondence: Brandeis Camp Institute.
    - 14 August, alternate title: God and Uranium were on our side
      - Correspondence (66), 1945 (Box 18)
      - Scripts (66), 1945; includes original teletype of first broadcast, two later broadcast scripts (Box 18)
    - Fragments from a Lost Cause
      - Correspondence (295), 1941 (Box 18)
      - Manuscript (295), 1941 (Box 18)
    - Good Heavens
      - Correspondence (296), 1941; 1948 (Box 18)
      - Manuscript (296), 1950 (Box 18)
    - Greetings With Variations
      - Typescript (89), 1950 (Box 18)
    - Hasten the Day
      - Recording [MISSING 6/12/2019], undated; phono record, original number LP-214
    - Home for the Fourth, Columbia Presents Corwin, Season 1 #1
      - Recording
        Broadcast over CBS on July 4, 1944, as the 17th in the first series of COLUMBIA PRESENTS CORWIN programs. Dane Clark appeared in the role of Ed Eakins, Wally Maher as Lt. Goggins,and Betsy Kelly, then the wife of Gene Kelly, played Rita. Bernard Herrmann composed and conducted the original score.
        - Home For the Fourth [disc 1 of 2], 07/04/1944; corwin_0281; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Home For the Fourth [disc 2 of 2], 07/04/1944; corwin_0282; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 8)
      - Miscellany (298), correspondence, review (Box 18)
    - The Human Angle
      - Manuscript, 1941 (Box 18)
        See also Television programs: The Human Angle.
    - John Brown's Body
      - Recording
        Adapted from Stephen Vincent Benet's epic poem, and directed and produced by Corwin over CBS on July 20, 1939. At this time an hour-long dramatization was extremely rare in radio. Corwin had been with the network a little over one year, and this was his first production from a Playhouse (on Broadway at 53rd street, New York City), and his biggest show up to that time. Ray Collins performed the role of John Brown; narrators included Frank Gallop and Everett Sloane. Due to a 10-minute timing error by a production assistant, ten minutes were cut by Corwin just before the program went on the air. the error was discovered half way through the live broadcast, with the result that Corwin was forced to drop the pace and "stretch" elements of the broadcast, in the latter half. Even with this heavy retard, the program finished some minutes under its intended hour. Adaptation not published. Corwin's personal acquaintance with Benet did not begin until 1941. The musical score was composed and conducted by Leith Stevens.
        - John Brown's Body Part 1 [disc 1 of 4], 07/20/1939; corwin_0228; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - John Brown's Body Part 2 [possibly other material] [disc 2 of 4], 07/20/1939; corwin_0229; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - John Brown's Body Part 3 [possibly other material] [disc 3 of 4], 07/20/1939; corwin_0230; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 7)
          John Brown's Body; CBS - "Harry James and his Music Makers" remote from Frank Daly's Meadowbrook, Part 1 of 2 (?). Scored out 2.0mil.
        - John Brown's Body Part 4 [possibly other material] [disc 4 of 4], 07/20/1939; corwin_0231; Lacquer discs/acetates
          Side A: John Brown's Body; Side B: CBS - Perry Como CBS - Raymond Scott and his Orchestra - "Fun with Dunn" Eddie Dunn - Live Scored Out.
    - Lip Service
      - Clipping about Adler (301), undated (Box 19)
      - Manuscript (301), 1941 (Box 19)
      - Script (301), 1941; final broadcast script (Box 19)
    - Log of the R-77
      - Correspondence (302), 1941; heavily annotated (Box 19)
      - Script, final (86), 1941 (Box 19)
      - Typescript (302), 1941 (Box 19)
    - The Lonesome Train, Columbia Presents Corwin, Season 1 #3
      - Recording
        Broadcast on March 21, 1944 as the third in the first COLUMBIA PRESENTS CORWIN series. It starred Raymond Massey, Burl Ives (singing the principal role) and Richard Huey, who played the role of the preacher in Alabama. Corwin directed but did not write the work; it was written by Millard Lampell, with music by Earl Robinson. Robinson himself was one of the cast, and called the square dance. Lyn Murray directed the orchestra and the Jeff Alexander Chorus. Unpublished. Several commercial recordings were made later, including one sung by Bing Crosby. Corwin directed the Decca recording, which consisted of the same company that appears in this disc, with the exception of Raymond Johnstone, who replaced Massey. The disc labels indicate that the recording is made for Gerald Kean.
        - The Lonesome Train [disc 1 of 2], 03/21/1944; corwin_0134; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - The Lonesome Train [disc 2 of 2], 03/21/1944; corwin_0135; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - The Long Name None Could Spell, Columbia Presents Corwin, Season 1 #2
      - Recording
        Presented as the second program of the first COLUMBIA PRESENTS CORWIN series on May 14, 1944, with Martin Gabel narrating. Others in the cast were Kermit Murdock, Giuliana Taberna, Joseph Julian and Carl Frank. William Shirer appeared as himself. The original musical score was composed and conducted by Lyn Murray. The script was originally written for an occasion at Carnegie Hall in honor of Eduar Benes, president-in-exile of Czechoslovakia, on May 28, 1943, at which time Berry Kroeger narrated and Stefan Schnabel, son of the pianist Artur Schnabel, was the Voice. This stage presentation was directed by Joseph Losey, who then went on to fame as a motion picture director in Europe. The Carnegie Hall version was published in MORE BY CORWIN; tha radio version, which was considerably expanded and improved, is unpublished. [A note on the sleeve's label indicates that additional data is in Envelope 159. On the disc's label is printed "Set B" and the date is 03/14/1944]
        - The Long Name None Could Spell [disc 1 of 2], 03/14/1944; corwin_0157; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - The Long Name None Could Spell [disc 2 of 2], 03/14/1944; corwin_0158; Lacquer discs/acetates (Oversize 5)
    - A Man with a Platform
      - Correspondence (303), 1941; 1946,; 1965 (Box 19)
      - Script (303), 1941; working script; includes casting sheet (Box 19)
    - Mary and the Fairy, 26 by Corwin #17
      - Recording
        Written expressly for Elsa Lanchester, wife of Charles Laughton, and broadcast from Hollywood on August 31, 1941, as the 17th of the 26 By Corwin series over CBS. Ruth Gordon played the Fairy. This germinal idea of the script was later expanded into the three-act comedy, THE HYPHEN. Hans Conreid played the bogus Rumanian prince. Script published in MORE BY CORWIN, Henry Holt & Co., 1944. On the sleeve's label is written that additional data is in Envelope 158. There is a hand written note on the disc's label indicating that the disc is property of Norman Corwin. Side 1: Part One; Side 2: Part Three
        - Mary and The Fairy Parts 1 and 3 [disc 1 of 2], 08/31/1941; corwin_0130; Lacquer discs/acetates
        - Mary and The Fairy Part 2 [disc 2 of 2], 08/31/1941; corwin_0131; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - Mary Had a Little Lamb
      - Correspondence and press material (127), 1938; includes items relating to Corwin's appearance with actress Peggy Burt (Box 19)
    - Million Dollar Club
      - Script (92), 1944; photocopy (Box 19)
    - The Moat Farm Murder, Columbia Presents Corwin, Season 1 #18
      - Recording